<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: c | Carpe diem (Felix's blog)]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/categories/c/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.idryman.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-07-05T08:59:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.idryman.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[dryman (Felix Ren-Chyan Chern)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing a memory allocator for fast serialization]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/2017/06/28/opic-a-memory-allocator-for-fast-serialization/"/>
    <updated>2017-06-28T12:19:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.idryman.org/blog/2017/06/28/opic-a-memory-allocator-for-fast-serialization</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my last post, I briefly introduced OPIC (Object Persistance
in C), which is a general serialization framework that can
serialize any object without knowing its internal layout.
In this post, I’ll give a deeper dive on how it works.</p>

<!--more-->

<hr />

<p>Still with the same disclaimer. I now work at google, and this project
(OPIC including the hash table implementation) is approved by google
<a href="https://opensource.google.com/docs/iarc/">Invention Assignment Review Committee</a> as my personal
project. The work is done only in my spare time on my own machine,
and does not use and/or reference any of the google internal resources.</p>

<h2 id="rationale-key-value-store-performance">Rationale: key-value store performance</h2>

<p>Key-value data retrieval is probably <em>the</em> most commonly used abstraction
in computer engineering. It has many forms: NoSQL key value store, embedded
key value store, and in-memory data structures. In terms of algorithm
complexity, they are all having O(1) amortized insertion, deletion, and
query time complecity. However, the actual performance ranges from 2K QPS
(query per second) up to 200M QPS.</p>

<p>To make it easier to reason about, here I only compare read only performance.
Furthermore, it’s single node, single core. In this setup, the data store
should not have transaction or WAL (write ahead log) overhead; if table locking
was required, only the reader lock is needed; if the data was stored on disk,
the read only load should trigger the data store to cache it in memory, and
the overall amortized performance <em>theoratically</em> should be close to what
in-memory data structure can achieve.</p>

<p>The first tier of data stores we look at, are the full featured SQL/NoSQL
database which support replication over cluster of nodes. A report created
by engineers at University of Toronto is a good start:
<a href="http://vldb.org/pvldb/vol5/p1724_tilmannrabl_vldb2012.pdf">Solving Big Data Challenges for Enterprise Application Performance
Management</a>. In this report they compared Cassandra,
Voldemort, Redis, HBase, VoltDB, and MySQL. Unfortunately, their report
doesn’t have 100% read only performance comparison, only 95% read is
reported.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Cassandra: 25K QPS</li>
  <li>Voldemort: 12K QPS</li>
  <li>Redis: 50K QPS</li>
  <li>HBase: 2.5K QPS</li>
  <li>VoltDB: 40K QPS</li>
  <li>MySQL: 25K QPS</li>
</ul>

<p>Some report gives even worse performance numbers. In
<a href="https://jaxenter.com/evaluating-nosql-performance-which-database-is-right-for-your-data-107481.html">this nosql benchmark</a>, 100% read, Cassandra, HBase, and mongo
are all having throughput lower than 2K QPS.</p>

<p>The performance of the databases above may be biased by network,
database driver overhead, or other internal complexities. We now look
at the second tier, embedded databases: LMDB, LevelDB, RocksDB,
HyperLevelDB, KyotoCabinet, MDBM and BerkelyDB all falls into this
category. The comparison of first four databases can be found in
<a href="https://www.influxdata.com/benchmarking-leveldb-vs-rocksdb-vs-hyperleveldb-vs-lmdb-performance-for-influxdb/">this influxdb report</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>100M values (integer key)
    <ul>
      <li>LevelDB: 578K QPS</li>
      <li>RocksDB: 609K QPS</li>
      <li>HyperLevelDB: 120K QPS</li>
      <li>LMDB: 308K QPS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>50M values (integer key)
    <ul>
      <li>LevelDB: 4.12M QPS</li>
      <li>RocksDB: 3.68M QPS</li>
      <li>HyperLevelDB: 2.08M QPS</li>
      <li>LMDB: 5.89M QPS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>The performance report from <a href="https://yahooeng.tumblr.com/post/104861108931/mdbm-high-speed-database">MDBM benchmark</a> is also interesting. They
only provide the latency number though.</p>

<ul>
  <li>MDBM: 0.45 us, ~= 2M QPS (?)</li>
  <li>LevelDB: 5.3 us, ~= 0.18 QPS (?)</li>
  <li>KyotoCabinat: 4.9 us, ~= 0.20 QPS (?)</li>
  <li>BerkeleyDB: 8.4 US, ~= 0.12 QPS (?)</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m guessing the performance number can be very different when the
keys are different.  In <a href="http://www.lmdb.tech/bench/microbench/benchmark.html">this LMDB benchmark</a>, LevelDB
only achieves 0.13M QPS.  We can see huge difference in the following
in memory hash tables. I ran these benchmarks myself. The code is hosted
at <a href="https://github.com/dryman/hash_bench">hash_bench</a>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>key: std::string
    <ul>
      <li>std::unordered_map: 5.3M QPS</li>
      <li>sparse_hash_map: 4.4M QPS</li>
      <li>dense_hash_map: 9.0M QPS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>key: int64
    <ul>
      <li>std::unordered_map: 106M QPS</li>
      <li>dense_hash_map: 220M QPS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This is the state of the art I have surveyed and experimented so far.
Clearly, the in memory data structure out performs all the other solutions.
There’s a big gap between the data store that can save to disk, versus
pure in-memory solutions. Can we fill the gap, and create a data store
with competitive performance to the best hash tables? This motivates me
to build OPIC (object persistence in C), where developer can focus on
writing fast in-memory data structures, and offload the serialization to
a general framework.</p>

<h2 id="rethink-serialization">Rethink serialization</h2>

<p>I like the clear definition in wikipedia that describes serialization:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>serialization is the process of translating data structures or
object state into a format that can be stored (for example, in a
file or memory buffer) or transmitted (for example, across a network
connection link) and reconstructed later (possibly in a different
computer environment).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In our case, we want to minimize this translation cost. The smaller
the translation cost, the faster the system can load the data.
Pushing this idea to extreme, what if the object have the same
representation in memory and on disk? This concept is not new.
Many modern serialization framework treats the serialized object
as an actual in memory object with accessors. <a href="https://developers.google.com/protocol-buffers/">Protobuf</a>
and <a href="https://thrift.apache.org">thrift</a> are two implementation for such idea. However,
neither protobuf nor thrift is capable to represent general
data structures like linked list, trees, or (large) hash tables. These
solutions lack of pointers; the only supported object relationship is
inline object or inline list of objects.</p>

<p>Why is pointer hard for serialization? If you simply copy the pointer
value for serialization, the address it pointed at would not be valid
after you restore it from disk. Most general serialization framework
would have to walk though all the related object user attempt to
serialize, copy all the objects, either inline the object or create
a special mapping of objects for cross references. In the current
state of the art, either you drop the support of pointer and get
minimized translation cost, or you pay high translation fee (walk
through objects) for general data structure serialization. How
can we do better?</p>

<p>Turns out, once you have a good way to represent the pointer value,
you gain the benefits of both solution: cheap serialization cost
and freedom to implement all types of data structures.</p>

<h2 id="key-idea-put-a-bound-on-pointer-addresses">Key idea: Put a bound on pointer addresses</h2>

<p>Pointers are hard to serialize because it can point to anywhere
in the full virtual memory space. The solution is pretty straight
forward, simply bound the objects into a heap space we control.</p>

<p><img src="/images/OPIC_memory_layout.png" alt="opic memory" /></p>

<p>Having all objects bounded in one memory space, serialization is
simply dumping the shaded memory out, and de-serialization is mmap the
file back in memory.  What if the objects contain pointers? Instead of
using pointers, we use the <strong>offset to the mmap base address</strong> to
reference objects. When accessing objects, we add the base address
back to the offset to reconstruct the pointer. Since we only use
the offset <code>opref_t</code> to store the pointer, even if the whole mmap
got mapped to a different address, we can still access the object
by adding a different base address to the offset. If we can ensure
all the pointers within the block are stored as <code>opref_t</code>, the whole
block of memory can be dumped out without any translation!</p>

<p><img src="/images/opref.png" alt="opic memory" /></p>

<h2 id="implementation-challenges">Implementation challenges</h2>

<p>Having zero translation (serialization/de-serialization) cost is very
attractive. However, building a POC took me a year (actually this is
the third version, but I omitted the details). Here are the challenges
I’ve found during the development.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>All objects need to be bounded in a memory chunk. Therefore I have
to write a full featured memory allocator. Writing a good one is very
time consuming.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Programming languages with run-time pointers, like vtables, pointers
in existing containers, etc. cannot be used in this framework. All
containers (hash tables, balanced tress) need to be rebuilt from ground up.
C++, Rust, Go all have their run-time pointers and cannot be used. The only
language I can use is pure C. (This is why the project is named Object
Persistence in C).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Serialized object cannot be transferred between architectures like
32bit/64bit, little endian or big endian. Depends on the use case, this
problem might be minor.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>These constraints shapes OPIC. The core OPIC API is a memory manager
for allocating C objects. All the objects created by OPIC would be
bounded in the 64GB mmap space. The 64GB size were chosen to hold
enough objects, while user can load many OPIC mmap files in the same
process.</p>

<p>Using OPIC malloc is very identical to standard malloc, except user
need to specify an OPHeap object where the object would allocated in.</p>

<p><code>c
OPHeap* heap;
// Initialize a 64GB OPIC heap via mmap
OPHeapNew(&amp;heap);
// pointer for accessing the object
int *a_ptr = OPMalloc(heap, sizeof(int));
// deallocate an object does not require specifying the heap
OPDealloc(a_ptr);
</code></p>

<p>What makes it different to regular malloc is, user can write the whole
heap to disk and restoring back via file handles.</p>

<p><code>c
void OPHeapWrite(OPHeap* heap, FILE* stream);
bool OPHeapRead(OPHeap** heap_ref, FILE* stream);
</code></p>

<p>To make your data structure work, you must store your pointer as
<code>opref_t</code> instead of regular pointer. Converting a pointer to <code>opref_t</code>
and vise versa is similar, except when restoring <code>opref_t</code> back to
pointer user must specify which <code>OPHeap</code> its belongs to.</p>

<p><code>c
// Convert the pointer to a offset to the OPHeap base address
// The pointer must be a pointer created by OPHeap
opref_t a_ref = OPPtr2Ref(a_ptr);
// Add the offset a_ref with OPHeap base address to restore
// the pointer.
int* a_ptr = OPRef2Ptr(heap, a_ref);
</code></p>

<p>In regular programs, user keeps their own reference of the allocated
objects. However, in the OPIC case, user would lost track of the
objects they allocated after the heap is serialized. This problem
can be solved by saving the pointers to the <em>root pointer slot</em>
that OPIC provides. Each OPIC heap offers 8 root pointer slot.</p>

<p>```c
/**
 * @relates OPHeap
 * @brief Store a pointer to a root pointer slot in OPHeap.
 *
 * @param heap OPHeap instance.
 * @param ptr the pointer we want to store in root pointer slot.
 * @param pos index in the root pointer slot. 0 &lt;= pos &lt; 8.
 <em>/
void OPHeapStorePtr(OPHeap</em> heap, void* ptr, int pos);</p>

<p>/**
 * @relates OPHeap
 * @brief Restore a pointer from specified root pointer slot.
 *
 * @param heap OPHeap instance.
 * @param pos index in the root pointer slot. 0 &lt;= pos &lt; 8.
 * @return The pointer we stored in the root pointer slot.
 <em>/
void</em> OPHeapRestorePtr(OPHeap* heap, int pos);
```</p>

<p>This API has been through many iterations. In the early version
it was a bunch of C macros for building serializable objects.
Fortunately it’s simplified and became more powerful and general
to build serializable applications. I believe it is now simple
enough and only require a little C/C++ programming skill to master.
Check out the <a href="http://opic.rocks/group__malloc.html">OPIC Malloc API</a>
for details</p>

<h2 id="performance">Performance</h2>

<p>OPIC can be used for general data serialization. The first data structure
I implemented is Robin Hood hash table – a hash map variant which has
good memory utilization without performance degradation. Memory utilization
affects how large the serialized file is, therefore is a one of the main
focus for writing OPIC containers. The details for keeping the memory footprint
small is in <a href="http://www.idryman.org/blog/2017/05/03/writing-a-damn-fast-hash-table-with-tiny-memory-footprints/">my previous post</a>.</p>

<p>The performance ends up super good: 9M QPS for in memory hash table.
For non-cached performance, I tested it by de-serializing on every
query. Every query would have to load the whole file back in memory
via mmap, then page fault to load the query entry. For this test I
got 2K QPS, which is 0.0005 second latency per load. Both cached
and non-cached performance are very promising, and perhaps is very
close to the upper bound for such application could perform.</p>

<h2 id="current-and-future-scope-of-opic">Current and future scope of OPIC</h2>

<p>Currently OPIC is implemented for building static data structures.
Build the data structure once, then make it immutable. User can
preprocess some data and store it with OPIC for later use. This
is the minimal viable use case I can think of for the initial release,
but OPIC can do more.</p>

<p>First of all, I want to make OPIC easier to access for more programmers.
Building high level application in pure C is time consuming, therefore
I’ll be writing language wrappers for C++, Python, R, and Java so that
more people can benefits the high speed serialization.</p>

<p>Second, I’ll make OPIC able to mutate after first serialization. High
level language user may treat OPIC as database of data structures
that one can compose. This kind of abstraction is different to
traditional database where program logic have to map to set of
records. I believe this will bring in more creative usage of new
types of applications.</p>

<p>Finally, I’d want to make OPIC to work on distributed applications.
I used to work on Hadoop and big data applications. I always wonder,
why people rarely talks about complexity and data structures in big
data world? Why there is no framework provide data structure abstraction
for big data? Isn’t the large the data size is, the more important
the complexity and data structure is? Building data structure for
super scale application, is the ultimate goal of OPIC.</p>

<p>Thank you for reading such a long post. If you also feel excited on
what OPIC might achieve, please post your comment. If you want to
contribute, that’s even better! The project page is at
<a href="https://github.com/dryman/opic">github</a>. Feel free to fork and extend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
